# Fernando Torales Acosta

🕥 ftoralesacosta | in fernando-torales-acosta | 🔗 ftoralesacosta.io | 🔀 fernandotta@gmail.com

## SUMMARY

Researcher working on machine learning developments for natural sciences. These include fast generative surrogate models, AI-assisted hardware design, deep learning for solving inverse problems, and implementing state of the art model architectures. Passionate about deep learning, engineering, and research.

#### Work Experience

#### Lawrence Berkeley National Lab – Postdoctoral Research Fellow

Feb 2022 - present

- Designed and executed experiments to evaluate the performance of generative diffusion models
- Achieved 150x reduction in disk space and 3x faster sampling time with no loss in model performance
- Developed Graph Neural Networks for AI-assisted detector design, achieved a 50% gain in precision
- Used deep learning to solve inverse problems for data correction, enabling completely new measurements
- Lead researcher, synthesized training data, containerized pipeline, and created tutorials for team

#### University of California, Berkeley – Graduate Researcher

Aug 2018 - Dec 2021

- Implemented parallelized data correction framework to decrease processing from 10 days to 4 hours
- Deep learning for background rejection, obtained 30% improvement over robust 15-year-old algorithm
- Updated data pipeline, converted petabytes of data, and sped up team's analysis tasks by 4x

## Projects

## Particle Feature Regression with Graph Neural Networks

GitHub Link

- Utilized DeepSets and Graph Neural Networks in the development of innovative physical detectors
- Established full data pipeline, data QA, model validation, and inference scripts for teammates
- Optimal detector design saved \$1M by showing expnsive alternatives were not required

## Comparing Stable Diffusion Models

GitHub Link

- Trained and compared diffusion models based on CNNs to models based on Point Clouds + GNNs
- Helped change inefficient paradigm of image-based modeling, and influenced later generative models
- Presented research results at a top-tier AI conference, resulting in the publication of a paper

#### EDUCATION

University of California, Berkeley Stony Brook University

Ph.D. (Physics)

2016 - 2021

B.S. (Physics)

2012 - 2016

## Relevant Publications

- Point Cloud vs. Image based generative diffusion: NeurIPS 2023 #192
- Optimal design of detectors using DeepSets and GNNs: DOI: 10.1088/1748-0221/19/06/P06002
- Isolated Photon-Hadron Correlation in ALICE: Phys. Rev. C 102, 044908

#### SKILLS

Python; C: Git: Pytorch; Tensorflow; Model Evaluation; Generative Models; High performanc computing Experiment Design; Software Development; Data Structures and Algorithms; Technical Writing